$$ All statistics in this film are from US
Government Studies $$
*[trumpet sound]*
*[helicopter whirring]*
*Today, the latest weapons coupled with
the fighting skill of the American soldier*
stand ready on the alert
all over the world to defend this country.
*You, the American people,
against aggression.*
*This is* The Big Picture.
*Now to show you part of * The Big Picture,
*here is Sgt. Stuart Queen.*
- The privilege of serving
the United States in uniform,
is no longer limited to men.
*[drum roll]*
♪ [music] ♪
*[Woman] The value placed by
the Women's Army Corps *
*on meticulous grooming
and feminine grace*
*is one of the first lessons l
earned by the recruit. *
*[Man on PA] There were demands
that would require of her *
*perfect physical health and stamina. *
- *Ladies, count.
- [All] One, two, three, four...*
*one, two, three, four.*
*[Nurse] I'm sure you've all
heard the saying, *
*"There's a right way, a wrong way,
and the Army way." *
*♪ Duty is calling you and me ♪*
*♪ we have a date with destiny ♪*
*♪ Ready... ♪*
*♪ the WACs are ready ♪*
*♪ Their pulse is steady ♪*
*♪ A world to set free ♪*
*♪ Service ♪*
*♪ we're in it heart and soul ♪*
*♪ Victory is our only goal ♪*
*♪ We're looking for ♪*
*♪ Computer specialists ♪*
*♪ Plane technicians ♪*
*♪ Plumbers...
Carpenters... ♪*
*♪ Electricians...
Art illustrators... ♪*
*♪ Statisticians... ♪*
*♪ Air controllers...
Security police... ♪*
*♪ Auto Mechanics...
Fire chiefs... ♪*
*♪ Look up ♪*
*♪ We look up to in the Air Force ♪*
*[Woman on PA] 2-1-2 radar contact*
*Turn right heading one-five-zero*
*[Man on PA] With the fog-bound helicopter
hanging on your every word,*
it doesn't matter whether you're a man
or a woman, only that you're good.
- *Coming up slowly...*
*♪ Be all that you can be. . . ♪*
*- [Pilot] Thanks for your help.
- Roger.*
*♪ 'Coz we need you in the Army ♪*
*[helicopter blades whirring]*
*[Female Pilot] I'm flying in a
helicopter right now.*
*[machine gun firing]*
Don't second‐guess yourself.
It's a lot of work, but it's totally worth it.
$$ The Invisible War $$
♪ [music] ♪
*[Kori Cioca] I would just always see
the movies of the military*
*and I just knew that was me.*
*That's what I wanted to do.
That's what I wanted to be.*
*There was a waiting list for
the Navy over a year*
and I knew I didn't want to wait that long.
So, I had a friend who told me
about the Coast Guard
and I went to the Coast Guard
and they said that they could get me in
within a month so I said,
"Okay, ship me off."
[Jessica Hinves] I tried college
and I had a good job
at a vineyard in East Texas.
I bought my own little house.
The military was something
I always wanted to do.
*I come from a military family.
I was always taught*
*that it's every citizen's duty
to join the military.*
*If you can, you should.
So, I want to go ahead*
and join and start a career.
*[aircraft taking off]*
*[Robin Lynn Lafayette] I joined the Air Force.
I was 17 years old.*
I had a boyfriend that encouraged me
to go in so that's what I did.
My mom signed, gave me permission to go.
*[Lt. Ariana Klay] When I was
in high school, *
*I was impressed with
the marines that I had met.*
*There used to be a lieutenant colonel
that used to run laps *
*around the track after soccer practice.*
And, he said,
"You'd be perfect for the Marine Corps
'cause you're really fit and smart
and that's what the Marine Corps needs."
The professionalism, the camaraderie,
everything about it inspired me.
[Trina McDonald] After I graduated
high school, I left for Orlando, Florida,
which was the first time I was
ever on an airplane in my life.
[chuckles]
*Initially, it was just wanting
to go see the world*
*'cause I'm from a really small town.*
*I had a college scholarship
to go play basketball*
*but I instead, opted to go
into the military. *
So, that's what I chose to do.
*[Lt. Elle Helmer] I come from a long line
of military lineage.*
Somebody from every generation
on both sides of the family,
*all the way back to the revolutionary war,
had served in the armed forces.*
*I chose the Marine Corps because*
*no one in my family had ever done it.*
[Hannah Sewell] I love putting on
a uniform every day
and, you know, just getting out there
and giving it my all.
*It's a very proud feeling.*
*[Everyone] 1, 1000... 2, 1000
3, 1000*
*He's a piece...*
[Kori Cioca] I would have done boot camp
over and over again.
*It was great, the camaraderie,
the discipline, everything it taught you.*
*Who I wanted to be.
That's what they taught you there.*
[Trina McDonald] Obviously it was different
taking a shower with 80 different people
all of a sudden 'cause I was pretty shy.
But, just a great experience.
*I was a 4‐0 sailor. Every single report done
on me was excellent, great.*
*I knew what I needed to do in my job.
I was a great team leader.*
*[Jessica Hinves] I really enjoyed the
whole challenge of it.*
I got several different awards and kudos.
*It was mainly men.*
*I loved that I could blend in
and keep up with the guys*
*and work as hard as they did.*
*[cheers and applause]*
*[Lt. Ariana Klay] The Naval Academy
was challenging.*
*The education was top‐notch.*
In my senior, I was selected to be in
one of the top 30 leadership positions
by the company grade officers there.
*[Trina McDonald] After basic, I went
to Naval Security Group in Adak, Alaska.*
*I remember getting there, you know,
issued a parka, I got set up in my room.*
And then he took me to the bar,
which was in our barracks
and sat down at a table where it was
me and about ten other guys.
And, you know, I kind of felt like a piece
of meat on a slab at that point.
And I'd never wanted to turn around
and leave so much in my life.
But I couldn't.
*- [Child[ Hey, mama.*
*[ball bouncing]*
*- [Kori] Go get it this time.*
- Okay.
*- [Kori] Get him, get him.*
- [Rob] Hey, you give me that ball.
*- [Kori] Give it to him derby style. Get him.*
[child laughing]
[Rob McDonald] I met Kori
December 17th of 2007.
I was on watch
when she got to the station
and she kind of just blew me away
when she walked in.
- Cookies, right?
Is it good you ordered?
Okay. Thank you.
- The command told us that
she was coming
and there were some issues
but none of the crew knew exactly
what had happened.
And I didn't find out for a long time.
*- For mommy?
Where's the heart?*
[Kori] He loved his job.
And it's kind of like he gave it up for me.
[Rob] She loved the Coast Guard
more than I did.
She wanted to make it a career,
but seeing how they treated her,
I didn't want to stay in.
I did it and then I did my extra year
and I got out.
I couldn't believe
what had happened to her,
and what she had went through.
[Kori Cioca] I was stationed in
Sagano, Michigan.
I was the only female in my section.
I had a supervisor.
It got to the place where I would
get calls at 3 o'clock in the morning
and he'd be drunk at a bar
telling me to come get him.
And I'm like "I cant, I'm in bed",
and he would then threaten me
I'd walk in from training
and he'd be sleeping in my bed.
When we went to
one of the higher‐ups
in the chain of command,
they were all like his drinking buddy
and they told me just because
I didn't like somebody,
they weren't going to switch me
away from this guy.
It was in the evening, around taps,
and he had unlocked the door
and he had come in,
and he had an erection
and he tried to get me to touch him.
I took my right hand and
I pushed him in the chest
and started to yell for the other guys
to try to kinda hear me, "Hey, hey, hey."
He hit me across
the left side of my face.
I remember holding the closet thinking,
"What just happened?"
And my face hurts so bad.
And when we went
to the command about it,
me and this petty officer
who saw my face,
they just let it wait cause they
didn't want any problems going on.
A couple weeks later,
I needed the key to do my cleanup
so I knocked on his door
and he said,
"Okay, yeah. come on in here.
It's in here."
And I said, "No, no, no,
I'm gonna wait out here."
And he said screamed at me
and he made me come in,
and he grabbed my arm
[sobbing]
and he raped me at his birthing area.
[Jessica HInves] Everything came
to a complete change
the day that I was raped.
[Trina McDonald] I got there in February
and by April
I was drugged and raped
for the first time.
[Robin Lynn Lafayette] I had a cold
or pneumonia-like symptoms
and so they sent me to get checked out.
And, while I was waiting to be examined,
he came in and he helped himself.
[Jessica Hinves] He said he was
going to the bathroom
and he came into my room
and that's when he raped me.
[Hannah Sewell] The entire time
I was screaming and yelling
for help and for him to stop,
nobody came to the door,
nobody came to help,
came to my rescue or anything.
[Trina McDonald] They made it very,
very clear that if I said anything,
they were going to kill me, you know,
and then of course,
I didn't have anyone to go talk to
because the people that
were perpetrating me were the police.
[Hannah Sewell] It was my first time ever,
and I've had a tough time
convincing myself that I'm still a virgin.
[Trina McDonald] If this is happening to me,
you know, surely I'm not the only one,
in which I find out later, going through
the claims process, that I wasn't.
$$ Over 20% of female veterans have been
sexually assaulted while serving. $$
[Robin Khale] It's just after 3 am, I see
a shadow of a human head over my body.
[Ayana Defour] Next thing you know,
like I wake up and like he's on top of me.
[Christina Jones] He pushed my legs apart
and put himself on top of me
and started pulling at my shirt.
[Debra Dickerson] And I wake up,
and he's on top of me.
He's already penetrated me.
[Regina Vasquez] I was drugged.
I remember the sounds, the smell.
[Lee Le Teff] He put his locked and loaded
45 at the base of my skull,
and gauged the bolt so that I knew
that it was around chambered.
[Katie Webber] All I could do was continue
to concentrate on breathing.
[Tia Christopher] He slammed my head
against the concrete wall
and very forcefully had sex with me.
[Jessica Brakey] I just went to my tent,
pulled the sleeping bag over my head
and cried myself to sleep.
[Teah Bedney] So, within the
two-week period,
he raped me five times.
[Valine Demos] When we got tested,
I had Trich and gonorrhea
and I was pregnant.
[Kristen Miller] And he did it.
He raped me.
[Amy Herdy] In 1991,
in Congressional testimony,
it was estimated that 200,000 women
had been sexually assaulted so far
in the US Military.
If you take into account that women
don't report because of
the extreme retaliation and that was,
you know,
more than a decade ago.
I would say you could easily
double that number
and it's probably somewhere near about
half a million women have now been
sexually assaulted in the US military.
[Capt. Anu Bhagwati] Well, according to
the Department of Defense,
3,230 women and men reported assault
in the last fiscal year, fiscal year 2009.
But they also admit, D.O.D itself,
that 80% of sexual assault survivors
do not report. So if you do the math,
16,150 service members
were assaulted,
which is an extraordinary number.
*[vial dropped]*
*[cluttering sound]*
- [Kori Cioca] We have more in the cars, Rob.
[cluttering sound]
There's some of it here, too.
This all was prescribed
in the last three to four months.
This is Proxatine, this is Seroquel,
Seroquel...**
Citolopram, this is Xanax.
I'm tired of taking all these meds.
I just want the VA to fix my jaw.
I was having the most horrible
pain in my face,
so I went to the dentist because
I thought it was my teeth
or something was wrong.
The doctor came in after the X‐ rays
and asked me if I had been
in a car accident.
When he hit me in my face,
he dislocated my jaw
and it sent both of my disks
forward in my face so I don't have
any disks where they should be in my face.
They told me I'd probably need a
partial bone replacement.
From where my bone had been laying
on my nerves for so long,
it's starting to actually disintegrate.
I've been on a soft diet for five years now.
I can't eat the foods that I used to eat.
Everything is mashed potatoes, Jell-o.
*[wind whistling]*
Well, I can go out
during the summer time,
spring time... if it's warm.
If it's too cold outside,
it's usually just Rob and Shea
go outside.
When it's really cold,
it's like my jaw would just lock up.
I just stand, watch from the window
and hear about the stories
when they come in.
*[Man on VA] We are sorry,
but due to a large volume of calls *
*and unusually long wait times, counselors
are unable to answer your call at this time. *
*[Woman on VA] Please stay on the line,
the calls will be answered*
*in the order received.*
*[Man on VA] 15 minutes could save
you hundreds on car insurance. *
*[Woman on VA] It's the Saint Louis
holiday tradition. *
*[Colbie Caillat playing on background]*
*[Man on VA] Hey, this is Stan. *
[Kori Cioca] Hi Stan, I just wanted to check
the status of my VA claim.
*[Stan] It's still on file on admissions,
let me check.
*
[Kori Cioca] Okay--
It looks like it's about a year old now.
[Kori Cioca] Yes, it is.
Okay it's still pending?
Did it say what status it was in?
*[Stan] Well, it looks like they've gathered
all the information that they need *
*but it still hasn't moved to the rating board yet.
*
[Kori Cioca] Okay.
*[Stan] Thank you for calling ma'am.
You have a good day. *
[Kori Cioca] You too. Thank you.
This is the stuff they prescribed me
for migraines
even though I don't have migraines.
So, I was looking online
and there are actually other vets
at the age of like, 25
and they would actually just die
because their body wasn't processing
because the mixture of the Seroquel,
the Gavapentin, the some kind of anxiety,
which was the Xanax
and, there was something else,
an antidepressant.
The mixtures of that stuff,
which is everything I have here that
other vets were taking
and they have died.
*[door shuts]*
- *Hey, baby girl. Hey, hey.*
- *Sit. *
[Hannah Sewell] Both my dad
and my brother are prior Navy
and now Army National Guards.
And it's kind of like it follows in the family
and follows the footsteps.
I was excited and completely
just hyped up about going.
All my family was proud of me.
My dad is my biggest hero.
[Sgt. Major Jerry Sewell] I told her, I said,
"You are going to be taken care of."
And I guess that's one of the hard things
that I have to accept because
I told her that she would be.
It was in February, we got a call.
$$ On February 1st 2008,
Hannah was locked in a hotel room
and raped by a fellow recruit. $$
[Hannah Sewell] Once he was done,
he rubbed his hand
all over my entire body
and told me, he said,
"I own all of this."
And I was just absolutely scared,
didn't know what to do.
I called my dad.
[Sgt. Major Jerry Sewell]
One of the first things she said is,
"Dad, I'm no longer a virgin."
And I said, "What happened?"
And she said, "I was raped."
And I said,
"Hannah, you're a virgin because
he took something from you
that you didn't give."
I said, "So, don't ever think you're not."
[Hannah Sewell] My main nerve
in my spine was pinched in three places
and my hips were rotated.
I could barely walk. I had collapsed due
to muscle spasms in my back
because my back
was injured during the rape.
[Admiral Anthony Kurta] My title is
Director of Military Plans
and Personnel policy for the Navy.
We have specifically trained
judge advocates.
Our Navy lawyers, in our naval criminal
investigative service,
those investigating are all specifically
trained in sexual assault.
Any report of a sexual assault
is fully investigated
in the United States Navy.
[Sgt. Major Jerry Sewell]
They didn't take care of it.
For a year and a half,
they were tracking down witnesses.
They had all these students there
and they could have locked them down
and said, "Hey you're on legal hold
and not leaving till I get this statement."
And they didn't. Hannah went through
three investigators.
It was like, "Okay I'm giving this case."
That's what it sort of felt like.
"Oh, alright I'm giving this case.
I'll take care of it.
Oh well this isn't even one.
I really don't have the time to deal with it."
[Captain Greg Rinckey] Females would
come up to their commander
or their NCOs and say that they were
either sexually assaulted or abused
and I don't think it was taken seriously.
I think a lot of times
a cursory investigation was done
and they were basically just told
to suck it up.
[Staff Sgt. Stace Nelson] I remember
bringing in a young service member
who had been brutally raped,
and bringing her in to see her command,
and trying to make sure that this
young girl was taken care of properly.
And this idiot, chewed her out for crying,
told her to stop crying over spilt milk.
[Captain Greg Rinckey] A lot of times,
the credibility of the witness
was called into account.
Had the potential victim,
had she made claims
like this in the past?
There was a lot of witch hunting going on.
[Maya Haider] I was ordered
to advise a victim of her rights
for false statement when I knew
that she wasn't lying.
I was asked to bring her in
and advise her of her rights,
like a criminal and interrogate her
for false statement,
"until I got the truth out of her."
If the woman makes a rape complaint,
they are always people asking
what she was doing there,
what she was wearing,
whether she had a boyfriend or not.
[Miette Wells] If any rape cases came in,
they were never given to women.
The men always took care of those
because we were too sympathetic.
We couldn't see what was really going on
because we always took the woman's side.
[Maya Haider] I was told
I should have been a social worker.
I had no business being
in the police field.
There was a lot of resistance there
toward the idea that victims should be
afforded some kind of sensitivity.
It was almost a laughing matter.
[Admiral Anthony Kurta] We have given
specific training and continual training
to our NCIS,
Navy Criminal Investigative Service,
those investigators on how best to respond
and to investigate those crimes.
[Hannah Sewell] They told me
they lost my rape kit
and my nurse examiners report and the
pictures from the bruising on my arm.
*[Amy] They lost these things? *
[Hannah Sewell] That's what they told me,
that they had lost them.
And me being me,
I decided to do a little digging
of my own and I spoke with
NCIS headquartersin Washington DC,
and they have all the evidence.
*[Amy] So what does this mean? *
[Hannah Sewell] Because the case
is already closed,
there's nothing they can do.
[Susan Burke] What we hear
again and again
from soldiers who have been raped,
as bad as it was being raped,
what was as bad, if not worse,
was to receive professional retaliation
in their chosen career,
merely because they were raped.
[Theresa Verderber-Phillips]
When you report something,
you better be prepared
for the repercussions.
[Debra Dickerson] If a man
gets accused of rape, it's a set‐up.
The woman is lying.
[Rebecca Catagnus] I could choose
to report it, but if they found that
what I was saying wasn't to be truthful,
then I would be reduced in rank.
[Allison Gill] You could lose your rate,
you could loose rank,
you could loose your school,
if you file a false report.
So do you want to file a report?
[Laughs]
[Christina Jones] Even with the rape kit
and everything,
and my friend catching him raping me,
they still don't believe me.
[Tandy Fink] I reported it two
different times to my squad leader
and he told me that
there was nothing he could do about it
'cause he didn't have any proof.
[Andrea Werner] They actually did
charge me with adultery.
I wasn't married. He was.
[Tia Christopher] They took me
before my lieutenant commander.
He says, "You think this is funny?"
I said, "What do you mean?"
He said, "You think this is all
a joke to you?"
I said, "What do you mean?"
And he goes, "You're the third girl
to report rape this week.
Are you guys like, all in cahoots,
you think this is a game?"
*[Man on VA] We are sorry,
but due to a large volume of calls *
*and unusually long wait times, *
*counselors are unable
to answer your call at this time. *
*[Woman on VA] Your name, please? *
[Kori Cioco] Kori Danielle McDonald.
*[Woman on VA] Okay, I show
that we've got a claim *
*open for non‐service‐connected
disability pension, depression, TMJ, *
*bilateral disk condition,
PTSD, nerve‐damage.*
*It's at the rating board in Cleveland. *
[Kori Cioca] Okay, and how long
does that usually take?
*[Woman on VA] Anywhere
from 102 to 139 days. *
[Kori Cioca] Really?
*[Woman on VA] And that's just
an estimated time. *
[Kori Cioca] 139 days?
I mean that's like--
I've already be waiting like 14 months.
What the fuck is going on up there?
What the fuck is going on at the VA?
Like, my shit is new?
And, it's 14 months?
I bet if we were there in person,
they would have to do something.
[car starts]
[car revvs]
Are you ready? Say ready.
Where are we going?
[both] Where are we going?
[chewing]
No, to the doctor.
Why are we going to the doctor?
What hurts on mommy?
My face, that's right.
- "You're gonna want to get on 75 North."
- " On 75 North?"
- "Yup."
This goes everywhere with me,
and then this goes everywhere with me.
You always have protection
with Jesus but sometimes
you need just a little bit more.
[Rob McDonald]
In doctor's appointments,
I come to every one just in case
she gets worked up
and she's uneasy about men already.
So, I have my phone up on me,
she has, I tell her to have
a text message or me on speed dial
if she needs to get out of there.
How did it go?
[Kori Cioca] It went good.
They, of course, ordered a back x‐ray
instead of a face x‐ray.
Here's some make‐up.
They should know
what's wrong with me.
Like read my stuff
and you'll see it's my face.
It's not my back, it's not my legs,
it's not my arms, it's my face.
[Rob McDonald] The people
who need your proof don't even know
what your case is about, like
I don't even know why we wasted
the gas money,
the trip, anything.
It was completely a waste of time.
What a good Veterans Day, right?
[Rob McDonald]
Yeah, it's a perfect way to spend it.
[Kori Cioca] Yeah, screw it.
[Rob McDonald] Alright, it's
around midnight on October 24th,
and Kori woke up, myself
and our baby.
She woke up screaming
so it's been happening quite a bit.
[crickets chirping]
- Okay, go go.
[leaves crunching]
- Oh!
- One more.
- I'm sorry I woke you up,
but it's fun, right? You're having fun.
- Let's put more.
- Yeah, let's put more.
I think Kori almost likes it better
because it's quiet
and you don't really know
what to run into at midnight.
[Trina McDonald] Because it was
in isolated duty station,
they kind of had their own world
of things going on.
They were in charge
and we were just kind of like, cattle.
The first time I was drugged
and raped, I was in this room
with some of my friends
and I only had like one or two drinks.
I went and laid down.
It was like instantly,
I was not feeling well and it came
to having a pillow over my head
and my friend raping me.
And that went on repeatedly.
You had to call an operator
to get a line off base so they listen
to your phone calls so they were screened
and I used to call my dad and begged him
to get me out of there.
He would always ask me,
you know, "Hon, well what's wrong?"
And I'm like,
"I can't tell you what's wrong,"
because the people who were listening
to our phone calls,
were the same people that could hurt me.
[Russell Strand]
Most sex offenders are hunters.
Just like any hunter,
they study their prey,
they study their movements,
they study their behaviors,
they study the environment.
[Staff Sgt. Stace Nelson] You have rapists
that prey on other human beings.
They stalk them,
they wait until the victim
is at the most vulnerable point in time
to perpetrate their crimes.
[Myla Haider] A lot of times
the victim is somebody
that the suspect is very familiar with
and they're very aware
of what's going on.
[Russell Strand] Most sex offenders
have this hidden persona
that nobody ever sees
other than the victim.
Therefore when they're caught
or when somebody reports,
people don't tend to believe that
because they don't see
the typical sex offender.
[Captain Greg Rinckey]
If it's an officer,
it's an officer that has habitually,
in the past, preyed on an enlisted.
They would do it once,
they would get away with it,
and then they think,
"Wow this is pretty easy,
I'm going to try it again."
[Brigadier Gen. Lorre Sutton] Particularly
for a savvy perpetrator,
to work with within a relatively
closed system, like the military,
it becomes a prime target rich
environment for a predator.
$$ A navy study found that 15 percent
of incoming recruits
attempted or committed rape
before entering the military.
Twice the percentage of the
equivalent civilian population. $$
[Trina McDonald] When I was discharged, I moved to
Seattle where things got really bad.
I started to lose everything.
I was homeless, there was addiction,
I was selling drugs, packing gun.
[Helen Benedict] Forty percent of homeless
female veterans have been raped
while they were serving. They spin into such
depression and abuse that they can't hold jobs,
they can't hold their lives together,
and they end up on the streets.
[Trina McDonald] My partner, Amy,
I met her a few years ago.
I was going and trying to do
some stuff at the gym.
[Amy Rosaaen‐McDonald]
When I first saw Trina
I was at the gym and I look over
and it was like the universe was like,
I was like, "Oh, there you are."
Well I knew there was something
"special" about her for sure.
When we first started dating,
it was hard.
The biggest hurdle
was not taking PTSD personally.
It does get really stressful.
[Trina McDonald] If I've ever lived
with anyone,
it's just been with that person.
So when I moved in,
it was like "Oh, my God",
you know, it was Amy, three boys.
[Amy Rosaaen‐McDonald]
I'm not just moving in with Amy,
I'm moving in with an entire family.
[Trina McDonald] So, they were so used
to such open space,
and with my PTSD,
we had some moments.
[Tim and Mitch Rosaaen] I'm sort of sad
to have never known Trina beforehand
when she was sort of in her prime.
Now she's anxious and sad a lot.
$$ Women who have been raped
in the military have a PTSD rate
higher than men
who've been in combat. $$
[Trina McDonald] A lot of times,
if we're out doing something,
you know, Mitch will be like, checking in
like, "Oh, it's okay Trina. It's alright."
I'm appreciative of it, you know,
but it makes me really sad
that here's this little 11‐year‐old boy
that's watching out for my well‐being.
It hurts. I want it to go away, you know,
and it doesn't go away.
[Russell Strand] I think that the men
that we attract in the military,
you know, we've got the army of one,
you know, be all you can be,
all those things we've had
for so many years
are very, very heavily masculine.
Masculinity cannot be victimized,
because if you're a leader,
if you're a masculine person,
and you're victimized, then you're weak.
The problem is anybody
can be a victim of sexual assault.
[Michael Matthews]
I joined the service in 1972.
The military is a great way of life.
I got to see the world, I got educated.
I loved the military. I was 19
and I went to the chow hall alone,
and the next things I know,
I was laying on the ground,
and I was struck from behind,
and two guys were holding me down,
and one guy
was pulling my pants down.
And, you know, he was
taking care of his business.
And you know I struggled,
and I was being struck and hit
and told to shut up or they'd kill me.
And I see how it destroyed my life.
I mean, I've been married three times.
Luckily I have a wife right now who
I've been married to for 25 years.
[Jeri Lynn Matthews]
You start wondering
and you start sort of,
you know either coming up
with reasons why things
are the way they are.
And for a long time, I kept thinking,
I don't know, there's something else.
[Michael Matthews] I had never told
anybody in over thirty years.
I decided to tell my wife.
It was the scariest moment of my life.
I was going to tell my wife,
she was going to leave me,
and I would be lost with out her.
I mean, honest to God,
I couldn't get up every morning
without my wife, you know.
And I told her.
[Jeri Lynn Matthews] I felt horrified,
and I felt sad and I felt angry,
along the course of the evening,
feelings just started to surface
that were probably just simmering
for a very very long time.
And she put her arms around me
and we just sat there and sobbed.
It was like, this great weight
had been lifted off of me.
[Brigadier Gen. Loree Sutton]
I think it's important to recognize
that military sexual trauma
is not limited to women,
and in fact,
when it comes to the absolute numbers,
because of the proportion of men,
in much larger numbers than women,
actually the numbers are even greater.
[Russell Strand] I think one of the
last bits of research,
showed that about 1% of males
had been victims of sexual assault
in the last year in the military.
That equals about 20,000.
[Jeremiah Arbogast] You would get labeled
as a 'buddy‐fucker'
and that's not a nice term
to be related to.
So, it's just one of those things
that you don't talk about
or you don't bring to anyone's attention.
You kind of just keep to yourself.
[Amando Javier] It's really, really
hard to forget.
You know up until now,
they live in my head,
I can hear them laugh,
I can see their faces,
I can see what they're doing to me.
[Brian Lewis] I felt scared
and I was scared to tell my friends,
the people that really knew me
the truth about what happened.
[Helen Benedict] The shame,
as bad as it is for women
is even worse for men, because
it's all tied in with homophobia.
[Susan Avila Smith] The people
who are doing the raping are not gay.
That's not the problem. They're worried
about gays in the military.
The gays are not the rapists.
They are heterosexual men
for the most part.
[Capt. Anu Bhagwati] This is not
an issue of sexual orientation,
this is simply an issue of power
and violence.
Male sexual predators
for the large part, have targeted
whoever is there to prey upon,
whether that's men or women.
[Brigadier Wilma Vaught]
Whenever I see, you know,
that there is evidence that another
woman has been sexually assaulted,
the question I keep asking myself is,
"When does this ever end?"
$$ 1991 Navy Tailhook. $$
*[Man on PA] Breaking news at this hour,
the navy appears to be facing *
*a huge sex scandal.
Details are still coming in. *
*[Announcer] From ABC, this is world news
tonight with Peter Jennings. *
[Peter Jennings] Good evening, we're going
to begin tonight by putting a human face
on the worst case of sexual harassment
in the navy's history.
At an annual Naval Aviators Convention
called, the Tailhook Convention,
*Senior officers have known since 1985
that the convention included *
*the so called, gauntlet,
set up for the specific purpose *
of targeting and sexually molesting women.
[Paula Coughlin] I got off the elevator
on the third floor.
You could see maybe 200 men.
It was just a few steps into the hallway
before they closed ranks all around me.
And then it happened very quickly,
from both sides and from behind,
many came in
and started reaching in my shirt.
I was getting pushed down to the floor
and someone was reaching under my skirt
pulling my underwear off, and you know,
and it was about maybe 30 or 40 feet
of 200 guys trying to pull my clothes off,
like I was a high valued target.
The next morning I met with
my boss for breakfast
and I said,
"You know, what happened here?"
And he said, "Well that's what you get
for walking down
a hallway full of drunk aviators."
And I said, "I don't think so. "
*[Peter Jennings] An investigation
was finally begun, *
*but 1500 interviews later,
the Navy's inspector general reported *
that his investigators
were being stone walled.
*A great wall of silence
had gone up to protect the guilty. *
$$ 1996 Army Aberdeen Proving Grounds $$
*[Man on PA] The US army today
is trying to establish the extent*
of a new and growing rape
and sexual harassment scandal.
*It all took place at the army base
at Aberdeen Proving Ground, *
*where 30 women have filed
complaints of sexual advances *
*ranging from unwanted touching
to rape and forcible sodomy.
*
*[Lt. Gen. Claudia Kennedy]
Aberdeen Proving Ground is a location*
*where the non‐commissioned officers
were assaulting and raping trainees*
and then passing the name of the person
they had assaulted to another NCO.
[Reimer] That unacceptable conduct
for soldiers,
it's unacceptable to the army
and we have zero tolerance.
$$ 2003 Air Force, Air Force Academy $$
*[Man on PA] Twelve years ago,
the Tailhook sex scandal*
*shook the US Navy
and now the Air Force faces*
*what may be an even bigger problem.*
[Peter Jennings] Rape and other
sexual abuse at the Air Force Academy
in Colorado Springs.
- 142 allegations of assault against women
have been made in the last decade.
[Shellee Smith] The highest ranking
Air Force generals knew about
serious problems of sexual assault
at the academy, yet failed to take action.
- We don't intend to sweep this
under the rag, we take it very seriously,
we're going to address it publicly.
- *In congress, outraged senators accused
Air Force brass *
*of ignoring assaults on women. *
[Sen. Susan Collins] We have a clear pattern
of reports of sexual assault
where the reaction
of the Air Force Academy
seems to be to blame the victim.
[Gen. John Jumper] We're in the process
of instituting those changes now.
[Sen. John McCain] You're in the process
of making those changes now?
Obviously you and I and the secretary
have a fundamental disagreement here.
$$ Present Day $$
$$ Secretary of Defense Confirmation Hearing $$
*[Sen. Clair McCaskill] What needs to be done
and what should be done,*
*as it relates to the problem
of sexual assault in the military,*
women in the military that have had
a great deal of difficulty
accessing some sense of justice.
[Leon Panetta] I really totally
share your concerns. We have to be--
we have to have zero tolerance for
any kinds of sexual assaults in the military.
$$ One mile from the US Capitol Building,
Marine Barracks Washington DC. $$
*[Man on PA] At a small post
in Washington DC, Marine pride,*
*history, and tradition live on.*
*Marine Barracks at 8th and I streets*
*is the oldest post in the corps
and for 100 years*
*since the early 1800s
Marine Corps headquarters. *
*[Donna McAleer] Marine Barracks
in Washington DC*
is the most prestigious unit there is
in the Marine Corps.
This is the unit where
the best of the best go.
It is the Marine Corps'
showcased ceremonial unit.
*It handles president's and dignitaries.
Security at the White House,*
*the Silent Drill Team.*
[Ariana Klay] After my deployment to
Operation Iraqi Freedom in 2008/2009,
*my command officer recommended me
for the Marine Barracks in Washington.*
*I was excited. It was the tip of the spears
as far as the Marine Crops is concerned.*
*[Capt. Ben Klay] She would stay at work late
and then she would drive home*
and she would call me and she would be
on some little sort of high
and tell me how she loves her job.
She was this sweet person who
was trying really hard in succeeding.
*[Ariana Klay] One of the first things
I was told when I checked in was,*
"Don't where any makeup
because the marines will all think
you're going to want to sleep with them."
And I thought, "That's just ridiculous."
[Elle Helmer] The atmosphere off the bat
at Marine Barracks Washington was horrible.
People asked me what sexual favors
had I performed to get my orders there.
*[Ariana Klay] There was senior officer
in my command,*
*who the first time he spoke to me,
he said,*
"Female marines here are nothing
but objects for the marines to fuck."
[Active Duty Marine] So, the minute a female
shows up at my work,
she is immediately pounced on.
All of the new females get talked about,
saying that they're having sex,
sleeping with so and so.
Apparently I slept with all these men,
and I mean, I didn't.
[Ariana Klay] It got progressively
worse and worse.
They determined that I welcomed the
sexual harassment by wearing
*my regulation length uniform skirt
and running in running shorts.*
There were several junior female
marines that came up to me crying,
while I was there saying that
they felt too humiliated to come to work.
$$ In units where sexual harassment
is tolerated, incidents of rape triple. $$
*[Elle Helmer] One of the duties at
Marine Barracks Washington,*
*was a ceremonial drill. *
The evening parades are what
you would see on the news.
The sound drill platoon, President,
everybody goes to those type of things.
[Ariana Klay] After the parades,
all of the officers
are required to stay til midnight
and drink at Center House
at Marine Barracks Washington.
So we're talking about Wednesday night
happy hours that start at three
and end at 2 am.
*[Active Duty Marine] It was a partying
and drinking culture.*
The atmosphere revolved around
going out and partying and drinking.
[Elle Helmer] I was ordered to drink,
I was ordered to attend the drinking events.
[Ariana Klay] My boss even said that they
were mandatory to me.
She's like, "We do our best work
at these events."
*[Elle Helmer] We went to various pubs
and bars and the goal*
*was to do a shot at each one.
All paid for by the Marine Corps.*
*[Arian Klay] You're talking about
drinking events,*
*where other senior officers are drinking
to the point of peeing in their pants*
you know, passing out on lawns.
This is the norm.
*[Elle Helmer] At one bar, I had water,
and I was ordered a shot anyway*
and was told I needed to take
two shots to make up for that.
$$ March 16, 2006. $$
*I left the bar to get a cab.*
My company commander followed me
and said,
"I need to talk to you about some things."
So we walked up the stairs in to his office.
*There was a little bit of a struggle.
He tried to make an advance*
*and try to kiss me. I tried to leave
and he slammed the door on my arms.*
*I fell on the ground and hit my face
on his desk*
and the next thing I realized was
I had woken up wearing his shorts
with all of my clothes off
and in tremendous pain.
I knew enough about me
that something wasn't right
and I had felt entirely violated.
$$ The day after the incident,
NCIS opened an investigation.
It was closed three days later
with no action taken.
Two days later, the base commander
initiated his own investigation. $$
The colonel at one point said,
"You know, Lieutenant Helmer,
boys girls and alcohol just don't mix.
We'll never really know
what happened inside that office.
Only you and the major know
and he's not talking.
So, at this point, the investigation
is closed for a lack of evidence
and we've reopened a new investigation
against you
for conduct unbecoming of an officer
and public intoxication."
[Active Duty Marine] I remember
going to the bar,
and there were officers,
they were buying shots for us.
After I had a couple of drinks,
that's all I remember.
$$ The same officer stalked and raped her
on three separate occasions. $$
This officer bragged
to his fellow officer friends
that he had 'bagged' me.
I got called up to a major's office
and he charged me
with fraternization and adultery.
He was married, I wasn't,
and I was charged with adultery.
*[Ariana Klay] I told the battalion XO
about the humiliation and the comments,*
and he said, "You know you should do
what a marine officer should do
and that's to ignore it and move on."
[Ben Klay] I used to lie awake in bed,
you know, wondering what I could do
to help her get out.
$$ After a weekly drinking event
in August 2010, Ariana was raped
by a senior officer 3and his friend. $$
[Ariana Klay] He said that if I told anybody
that he was going to have his friend Marve
from Indiana kill me and throw me in a ditch,
because that's how they
took care of things in Indiana.
[Ben Klay] She went to war and
gave nine years of her life,
and for them to take it
and come back and say,
"Yes they called you a whore,
yes they called you a slut,
yes they called you a walking mattress,
it's documented
over and over and over again,
but you deserved it
and when you complained about it,
you were welcoming it."
[Ariana Klay] The actions of my seniors
both in the assault and in the ensuing
investigations have really destroyed me.
[Capt. Ben Klay] When your wife
doesn't come home to--
rummage through the house
searching for the suicide notes,
to call the police with one hand
while you're restraining her
from killing herself with the other.
*[Ariana Klay] I think the thing
that makes me the most angry*
*is not even the rape in itself,*
it's the commanders that were complicit
in covering everything up that happened.
$$ The filmmakers contacted
five female marines
who were each assaulted by an officer
while serving at Marine Barracks Washington.
Four of the women were investigated
or punished after they reported.
No officer was punished for any assault. $$
*[Capt. Ben Klay] This is an organization
that gives commanders*
an unbelievable amount of power.
And I felt it, as a lieutenant in Iraq,
it's scary. You appoint the prosecution,
you appoint the defense,
you appoint the investigator,
you're in charge of the police force,
you're in charge of the community.
You own everything. You are judge,
you are jury, you are executioner.
[Susan Burke] Most Americans assume
there is access to a system of justice,
so that, for example if you're a civilian
and you're raped, you can call the police
and then you have prosecutors,
either federal prosecutors, state
prosecutors, local prosecutors,
that bring the perpetrator to justice.
The problem with the military is that
they instead have to go
to their chain of command.
[Admiral Anthony Kurta] Now in our
system of military justice,
it is the commander who's responsible
to the chain of command
for how that investigation proceeds.
[Stace Nelson] I know that there's been
numerous times over my career that I
regretted that an individual commander
had the total say so over a case.
Most of them don't have the training
or the education to determine
what's appropriate and
in serious felony investigations.
[Captain Greg Rinckey] The problem
in the military is the convening authority
who is not legally trained,
makes the final decision.
[Jessica Hinves] They had
a change of command
at my old squadron where the guy
that raped me was still stationed.
He had only been in command
for four days,
and he made a decision
over legal to stop the case.
[Capt. Anu Bhagwati] What I saw
was commanders,
and these are field grade officers,
lieutenant colonels,
colonels who have been in 20, 25 years,
they are career officers,
and they sweep cases under the rug.
[Major Gen. Dennis Laich] The last thing
a company commander in the army
wants to do, is make the phone call
to his or her battalion commander to say
I have had an allegation
of a rape in my unit.
This is viewed in many cases
as a failure to command
that will adversely then
affect their career.
[Stace Nelson] Sometimes you would see
a guy get four or five years for selling
a minor amount of drugs,
and then you would a guy
get two weeks extra duty for rape.
[Susan Burke] The military hides behind
this notion that it is really, really hard.
Almost impossible to prosecute rape.
*But when you look at prosecution rates*
*in the 2010 Department of Defense reports,
you begin with 2,410 unrestricted reports*
*and 748 restricted.*
*What this means is they've already
funneled 748 sexual assault victims*
*into a system that has absolutely
no adjudication whatsoever.*
*Then you take the 2,410
that have been reported,*
*of those they have identified
3,223 perpetrators.*
*Now what happens
once you send a perpetrator*
*over to command?
Well, the command has just completely*
*unfettered discretion to do
whatever it is they want.*
*And what is it that they do do?
First off, they drop 910 of them,*
*they just don't do anything. Then of the
1,025 that they actually take some action,*
*do they court martial them? No.
Only half of them, 529,*
*actually got court-martialed.*
*The rest, 256 were subjected to
Article 15 punishments,*
*109 to administrative discharges,*
*and 131 to "other adverse administrative
actions",*
*whatever the heck that means.*
*And then of the convictions
where they actually get jail time,*
*when you work your way all the way
through the numbers,*
*what you're looking at,
is that out of 3,223 perpetrators,*
*only 175 end up doing
any jail time whatsoever.*
*[Louise Slaughter] I have been
in congress for seven terms now,*
and every single term,
we have had meetings with D.O.D
and they come in and they confirmed
to us, "We're going to be serious,"
"we're going to take care of this,
we're going to stop this, zero tolerance."
But the rhetoric is not being turned
into the reality of protecting our women,
and in some cases men in our military.
[Susan Avila Smith] So then they're like,
but we have this SARC
and SAPRO program, it's like,
"Oh great."
*What does that do?*
*They can strongly suggest to the
military to do something.*
*- As a band of brothers and sisters,
it is our personal duty*
*to prevent sexual assault*
- They can't order them, they can't
enforce it, they don't back it up.
[Dr. Kaye Whitley] In April of this year,
we will debut
a social marketing campaign
as part of our prevention strategy.
- *Preventing sexual assault
is part of my duty*
-* So when I saw my buddy's date was drunk
I told him, "Ask her when she's sober" *
*[Capt. Anu Bhagwati] It's ludicrous,*
it's 2011 and we have posters
that say, "Wait until she's sober."
I mean, it's remarkable that
that's allowed to pass in today's military.
[Dr. Kaye Whitley] Well, we've implemented
training at each entry level
of military service from the moment
they enter the service and basic training.
They are given that.
*And, our campaign consists
of a series of posters that are actually*
*training tools and each of those posters
has a different focus.*
[Capt. Anu Bhagwati] You cannot prevent
sexual assault with pretty posters.
Posters do not prevent sexual predators
from preying upon women
and men in the military.
We're talking about barging into rooms
in the middle of the night.
No poster can prevent a criminal
from barging into your room.
These are violent people.
[Dr. Kaye Whitley] Well one of the things
that we do in our prevention strategy
is to focus on bystander intervention.
And in that strategy and in that training
we ask each soldier, sailor,
airman and marine,
to be aware of what sexual assault is
and how to prevent it.
[Jessica Hinves] SARC is a joke.
*The things that are said are ignored
or they're made fun of.*
♪ [Music] ♪
- [Ariana Klay] There may be a video,
or 20 slides.
It's like a lot of military training
where it's the once of the year,
check in a box.
♪ [Music] ♪
- [Capt. Anu Bhagwati] SAPRO can't fix anything.
- You walkin' back alone?
- Yeah, It's just a short walk to my tube.
- Alright.
- *And all the money seems to be
spent on advertising,*
*which is just rife with victim blaming.*
- What's your name?
- Stop.
- Hey, come here. I just
wanna talk to you for a sec--
I just wanna talk to you.
*[running footsteps]*
- Whoa! Are you okay?
- No. There's this guy, he grabbed me.
- Why are you by yourself?
Where's your buddy?
- I didn't think I needed one.
- *[Narrator] Sexual Assault is preventable.*
*Are you doing your part?*
- [Susan Burke] And so this notion that
essentially anyone could be a rapist
and we all have to be alert.
It misses an opportunity to take real steps
towards preventing rape.
If they actually had systems
of accountability that prosecuted
and imprisoned perpetrators,
you would get rid of
a lot of the rapes right away.
- *[Kirby] How would you characterize
the typical sex offender? *
- [Dr. Kaye Whitley] Well, if I look at
the data from the Department of Defense,
it is young people that are ages 18
to 24 or 25.
*[Kirby] Would you say that most of them
are serial rapists? *
- [Dr. Kaye Whitley] I don't have data
one way or another to determine that.
- *[Kirby] And what percentage
of the rapes do you think *
*are caused by serial predators? *
- [Dr. Kaye Whitley]
I don't have any numbers.
I don't think we collect that type of data.
- *[Kirby] There have been studies done, *
*that people who enter the military are
twice as likely to have committed rape *
as the equivalent population
in the civilian world.
- [Dr. Kaye Whitley] I'm not aware
of that study.
My area of expertise focuses primarily
on prevention and victim care.
- *[Kirby] But, wouldn't prevention include
focusing on the perpetrators? *
$$ July 31, 2008, Kaye Whitley
is subpoenaed to testify
before the House Subcommittee on
National Security and Foreign Affairs. $$
-* [Congress Chairman] I noticed that
Dr. Kaye Whitley is not in her chair.*
Is it under your direction that she
is not showing for testimony
this morning?
- *[Dominguez] Yes sir.*
- [Congress Chairman] You directed her not to?
- *[Dominguez] I did. *
- [Congress Chairman] Do you have an
executive privilege to assert?
- *[Dominguez] No, Sir.*
- [Rep. Henry A. Waxman] You've
instructed her not to come?
What is your reason for doing that?
[Dominguez] If you find
the department's response
and prevention efforts fall short
of your expectations,
responsibility for that shortfall
rests with me.
- *[Rep. Henry A. Waxman]
That's a ridiculous answer.*
*What is it you're trying to hide? *
We all remember Tailhook and the scandal,
and how the military tried to cover that up.
*I don't know who you think elected you*
*to defy the
Congress of the United States,*
we're an independent
branch of government.
- [Congress Chairman] So for now
Mr. Dominguez, you are dismissed.
- *[Kori Cioca] Intimacy is definitely affected.
We'll go months without sex.*
I have to initiate,
if I'm comfortable enough,
if I'm having a good day, and I think
my husband looks hot for the day,
I have to initiate.
When he comes up and hugs me,
sometimes I'll cringe
and I'll just want him to--
he'll feel it, and then he'll get mad
because he'll be like,
"Why aren't you hugging me back
or whatever?"
- [Rob McDonald] I still do that.
- [Kori Cioca] I don't like him
grabbing my hips.
- [Rob McDonald] I didn't understand
why because it's like,
"I'm you're husband, why?"
and I don't fully understand now.
- [Kori Cioca] I see it in my dreams.
That's what you don't get,
I don't want to talk about stuff,
and you know that.
- [Rob McDonald] Yeah well that's
the hard part, I don't know--
I want to help you, but I don't know,
you know?
- [Kori Cioca] You can't help me.
That's the thing, cause you can't.
*Sometimes I think, if when he's
have sex with me,*
is he thinking about me getting raped,
is he upset, is he, you know,
because I think about that, and never
does it not run through my head.
*That's why I didn't want
to have sex for a while.*
- [Rob McDonald] What if you
were in my spot?
- [Kori Cioca] It would suck so bad.
I'm not saying I don't appreciate you,
But it make me cry, baby,
this is why I don't talk about it Rob,
because it does upset me.
Like when we almost split up
'cause of stuff,
and I feel like I'm responsible for it.
I don't know what I'd do if I lost Rob.
I'd be so lost.
He's like my only supporter.
Like my own blood.
*- [Amy Herdy] I've interviewed women
in the civilian world,*
and rape is a very traumatizing thing
to have happened,
but I've never seen trauma
like I've seen from women
who are veterans who have
suffered military sexual trauma.
- [Stace Nelson] I cannot remember
how many times
a young female marine
that had been raped
or sexually assaulted had told me
that she looked at these guys
as her brother,
or the suspect as her brother.
- [Brigadier Gen. Loree Sutton] It's akin to
what happens in a family with incest.
Because in the military, when we're
functioning at our best in a cohesive unit,
what brothers and sisters, you know,
the band of brothers and sisters,
I mean we are family.
When that bond of trust is violated,
the wound penetrates to the very most
inner part of one's soul, one's psyche.
[Kori Cioca] I have this folder that I keep.
I have all my boot camp letters in it,
from my mom and my sister
and I was just going through it
and I was like, "What is this?", and I was
like, "Oh my god, my suicide letter."
"Mom, I'm sorry for the grief
that you must feel.
Just because I'm gone physically
doesn't mean I won't be there spiritually.
I truly feel that God will
take me without question,
even though I took my own life.
I've had the most broken thoughts,
dreams, and physical pain to remind me
of the horrific acts upon me
that happened while on duty. A mother,
brother, sister and husband should
never live knowing the acts upon me,
find peace in knowing that the body
left behind doesn't consume my soul.
I am free now, and not afraid.
Ready to soar, Kori Danielle."
[Trina McDonald]
I took a whole bottle of pills.
And woke up strangely enough,
I'm not sure why.
At that point in my life
I just wanted it to be over.
I think I was 20, 21 and then
within the next year, I tried again.
[Michael Matthews] I went out
into the garage,
which was separate from the house,
and I turned the car on.
I was going to sit in the car
and asphyxiate myself.
And we have this little poodle,
Blondie,
she went out in the little doggy door
and she's scratching at the door,
and I'm like, "Shut up, Goddammit!
You're going to wake my wife up."
So I get out, shut the car off,
and I thought for a moment,
maybe I'll just take her
in the garage with me,
and I thought,
"Why would you kill a dog?"
And then I thought,
"Well why would you kill yourself?"
[Hannah Sewell] I thought of it,
so many times,
and in so many ways. I thought about,
at one point in time,
hanging myself from the flagpole,
with a sign on me saying exactly
what happened, to make him feel bad.
[Kori Cioca] I was going to overdose
on pain medication
and sleeping medication
and hope that I would fall asleep
and my body would just shut down,
or do something.
When I went to the doctor,
I had been feeling sick,
and dizzy and nauseated,
and they took my urine
and they told me
that I was pregnant.
And it was like, there's a life in there,
and maybe her life
will be better than mine,
and I've got to make sure of that.
So, she's very special.
[Brigadier Wilma Vaught] Sometimes
it takes a different kind of action
to cause change to come,
and sometimes that's a lawsuit.
[Susan Burke] I grew up on military bases.
My dad was career army.
When I was a child,
when we answered the phone,
we would have to say,
"Colonel Burke's quarters,"
and because of that,
I have the understanding of the
level of control
that perhaps most
in the civilian life don't have.
The Feres Doctrine
is a judicial doctrine
that was developed by
the Supreme Court that says,
although the United States
is going to allow people
that are hurt by the government,
to sue, just as you could sue a company,
congress could not possibly have meant
to include the military in that.
Now Congress did not actually say that,
rather it's a judicial interpretation
of what they must have meant.
If you're in the military,
you cannot sue for something
that happens to you
that's incident to your military service.
If military doctors amputate the wrong limb,
you're out of luck.
You can not sue for that harm
that's been done to you,
so we filed a law suit in federal court
on behalf of 16 men and women,
seeking to bring
former Secretary Rumsfeld
and Secretary Gates to justice.
[Kori Cioca] I heard about the lawsuit
and decided to become a part of it
because I never wanted
another woman
to go through what I went through.
[Susan Burke] The law suit alleges
that they have overseen
a system that has deprived the
rape survivors their constitutional rights,
specifically we alleged
that they deprived them
of their substance of due process,
their procedural due process,
equal protection
and first amendment rights.
[Kori Cioca] It made me sick
to see everybody's stories.
How they kind of closely tie together.
It's consistent, like what
the military does to us.
[Myla Haider] All the things that they've
put in place are all pretty much intended
to help women deal
with being raped better,
that's what they're about.
[Myla Haider] I joined the military
halfway through
my senior year of high school,
wanting to serve my country
and do new things
and challenge myself in a different way.
I was in the army for about 7 or 8 years
before anything happened to me.
I was raped by another CID agent
who was senior to me.
I was contacted by an agent
with Fort Riley CID,
who said theywere investigating
the suspect as a serial rapist
who had raped several military
law enforcement women.
I thought, you know, there was
no way he wouldn't be convicted.
If I have a difficult time with anything,
it's about the fact that I had
an almost ten-year career
that I was very invested in, and I
gave it all up to report a sex offender
who was not even put to justice
or put on the registry,
and he's probably doing
the same thing right now.
[Sarah Albertson]
I had one female lieutenant
pull me aside and tell me she had heard
about her case
and she thought she could talk to me
from one female marine to another,
and she said,
"Well what he did, was capitalize
on an opportunity
that you presented him.
That's not the same thing as rape,
you need to know that.
A month after it happened, they made me
go on a hike with him,
and I tried to make everyone
advocate for me not to go
because I just couldn't deal
with seeing him,
so their solution to that
was to put him in front of me,
so that I could see him the whole time,
so that I could know where he was
and know that he
wasn't able to do anything
because he was standing
right in front of me.
And I remember thinking the entire time
we were up on the hills,
up at Camp Pendleton,
if only it was steeper,
I would have jumped.
[Myla Haider] There's no way out of it,
I mean if you think of it,
the only way out of it
is suicide or AWOL.
Those are your only options.
Suicide, AWOL or deal with it.
[Regina Vasquez] Right now,
I'm just barely appreciating
learning how to appreciate
being a woman again.
That's 11 years,
and I'm trying to have fun with it,
not forcing myself to have fun.
I'm trying really hard not to cry
but it just pisses me off.
Watching you girls having to go
through what I have
it makes me want to explode.
[Kori Cioca] Being here, me wanting to
commit suicide, I'm not alone.
Me being hit and raped, I'm not alone.
Everything.
The way that they treated me, the way
that they made me feel, I'm not alone.
And we have all of you guys, with all
of your knowledge and everything
you guys are going to stand right up,
you know, that's awesome.
That's all I'm saying.
[Brigadier Wilma Vaught] I think the women
who are coming forward
in this law suit are very courageous,
because they're putting their names
out there for criticism
they're putting their names out there
in history
as they were the ones who got raped,
and that's not anything you want
to go through life with.
[Capt. Anu Bhagwati] Today I stand
in solidarity
with the courageous women and men
who have served in our armed forces.
The inspirational plaintiffs
you see before you are a small handful
of the tens of thousands
of troops and veterans
who have been sexually brutalized
by their fellow service members
while defending our nation.
It is time to finally acknowledge
that our military's judicial system
is broken when it comes to these cases.
[Kori Cioca] My name is Kori Cioca
and in my case, my command
was unwilling to help me.
I went for help many times with my
petty officers and I was denied help,
even with other men saying,
"Please get her away from him.",
and it was still allowed.
[Sarah Albertson] My name is
Sarah Albertson.
People were telling me,
"Don't go to the public because
it will make the military look bad."
[Myla Haider] I really feel like it is
my social responsibility
to speak out about this issue,
especially considering my
investigative experience and especially
because the military justice system
allows so many offenders
to escape justice.
[Kori Cioca] She's actually starting
to play with her toys.
[Myla Haider] Imaginative playing.
[Kori Cioca] It's all the stuff
that you teach them
when they play, you know.
It's really cool.
[Myla Haider] I miss my baby.
[Kori Cioca] I do, too.
Thank you for having us.
[Rep. Chellie Pingree] Sure.
Thanks for being willing to fill me
in a little bit on the experiences.
[Regina Vazquez] My name is
Regina Vazquez and I served honorably
in the United States Marine Corps
for four years.
[Kori Cioca] My name is Kori Cioca
and I served in
the United States Coast Guard.
I was harassed
and sexually assaulted.
[Myla Haider] I was administratively
discharged with no benefits
after nine and a half years of service.
[Rep. Louise Slaughter] Women
should not have to bear that burden.
That is not part of what we should have
to be doing to be doing our jobs.
[Rep. Mike Turner] We're talking
about criminal activity.
We're talking about a vicious attack
that is criminal. It is an assault.
[Myla Haider] Almost none of the cases
made it to court‐martial,
and out of the ones that do,
almost none of them result in conviction.
[Loretta Sanchez] It seems to me
all the times
that I've looked at these things
that the command is the one
who has such so much discretion.
[Kori Cioca] I think the advocate
should actually be civilians.
Not ones that work in the military.
I think we should have actual units,
civilian units.
[Rep. Jackie Speiere] It absolutely tears
my inside to think
that this has been going on
as long as it's been going on
and we've never addressed it.
[Rep. Ted Poe]
All people in the military must know,
if you're a perpetrator of sexual assault
against someone else in the military,
we'll be to you.
You're going to be held accountable.
[Myla Haider] As a CID agent,
I found it tremendously frustrating
when I would demonstrate that
an offender had committed an offense,
and taking it to a commander
and having a commander
being the deciding authority.
You know, I don't think commanders
are capable
of making an objective decision.
I do not think it should be in their hands.
[Rep. Niki Tsongas] So you would suggest
taking the discretion away from them?
[Myla Haider] Yes, absolutely.
[Rep. Niki Tsongas]
Congresswoman Davis and I
are both on the
armed services committee.
[Rep. Susan Davis] There are
a number of issues
that you've raised
that makes me want to go back
and particularly take another look.
[Rep. Loretta Sanchez] On an
emotional basis,
what happens after a crime like
that has been committed
is a difficult thing to go through,
and don't think I don't know. I know.
[Rep. Chellie Pingree] The fact
that you're willing to tell us
your stories first hand,
makes it much easier for us to go back
and to say you know these are policies
we have to change.
It's a big deal what you're doing.
[Kori Cioca] You rarely find people
who stand up for us,
and just thank you so much
for everything that you do.
[Rep. Ted Poe] Last year,
the military received over 3,000 reports
of sexual assault involving
other members in the service.
This week, 17 veterans are saying
the military ignored their cases
of sexual assault
while they were on active duty.
[Rep. Jackie Speiere] Today I'm going
to talk about seaman Kori Cioca
who served in the Coast Guard
from August 2005 to June 2007.
She now suffers from PTSD
and an abnormal EEG
due to nerve damage in her face.
Cioca later told the press,
"It's like they didn't care.
It wasn't important,
I wasn't important."
[Kori Cioca] So, we're eating
at Bob Evans'
and I overhear a girl
talking about getting ready
to go into the military,
so I go over there and try to talk to her.
Has anybody told you what to
watch for or anything?
[Waitress] My boyfriend's in the navy.
[Kori Cioca] So, he knows
how tough it is for women.
[Waitress] Yeah, he's been in
for a couple of months now.
[Kori Cioca] So, how does he feel
about you joining?
Like, isn't he scared that the men
will do something?
[Waitress] He's a little scared
but he knows I can take care of myself.
[Kori Cioca] Oh I thought so too,
so be careful.
I definitely let her know that maybe
she should reconsider college
and getting a degree.
It'll save her some of the trouble.
I wish someone would have told me that.
You try to take care okay?
You can still back out.
You can be a civilian worker.
[Wairess] Yeah, thank you.
I'm not signed yet.
[Kori Cioca] Okay, well, just be careful.
[Maiette Wells] People always ask me,
"Was it worth it going in?"
The idea of it is honorable.
Serving your country is great.
There are good people in it,
and then there are people
who will end up ruining your life.
[Lt. Ariana Klay] Just the other day,
I saw a girl running along the road.
She looked like she
was about high school age.
She was wearing a USMC T‐shirt,
and I thought that, if she joins,
then she's going to have to accept rape
and destruction of her life.
I cannot in good faith, I cannot recommend
anyone to join with the way
the organization is set up now.
I would not wish that on anyone.
[Rep. Chellie Pingree] You can't ask
women to serve
and then say, "Oh by the way, if you get
in one of these horrendous situations,
we won't be there to back you up
or to help you."
[Rep. Loretta Sanchez] When I would do
nominations for the air force academy,
it was difficult to talk to parents
and say,
"Don't worry, she's not going to get raped."
[Christina Jones] No. I would tell
my daughter not to join the military.
They have good things to offer
but a rape is not one of them.
[Miette Wells] Not in my lifetime.
She's not joining, no.
[Rob McDonald] I would be terrified
if my daughter wanted to join the military.
I would have a serious long talk
and hope that the one thing
is that's what she'd listen to.
[Brigadier Gen. Loree Sutton]
Losing even one soldier,
needlessly, because of military sexual
trauma, is one too many.
[Kori Cioca] I'm going to get the mail.
Fingers crossed. Here's my fate.
[Rob McDonald] What does it say?
[Kori Cioca] Effective October 20th 2009.
My overall combined rating is 70%.
Wait. Service connection for anxiety
is denied,
service connection for disk placement
and bilateral disk displacement
is denied.
Those motherfuckers, man.
Oh, my god.
My face doesn't have any disks in it,
that's what the x‐rays show.
[Rob McDonald] How can you deny
medical help when there's x‐rays?
If you do not agree with our decision
you should write us and tell us why.
[Kori Cioca]
'Cause you're an asshole.
[Rob McDonald] And you
should identify specific issues.
[Kori Cioca] You're an idiot.
[Rob McDonald] The evidence
that was reviewed showed that
you served whatever, which is less than
minimum active duty requirements
for disability pension.
But it wasn't your choice.
[Kori Cioca] They're going
to punish me for what they did,
because I was short two months
of two years. I know.
I feel the same way, Shea.
[Dr. Kaye Whitley] It's nice to see you again
and thank you for coming.
You have been provided highlights
of the numbers of the report
and I'm going to walk you
through those slides,
then I'm going to play a short
public service announcement
and then we can entertain questions.
I think the prevention aspect
of sexual assault
goes back in some ways to risk reduction.
*[Kirby] What is risk reduction? *
[Dr. Kaye Whitley] Risk reductions
are ideas like telling women to--
if they're going to go somewhere,
always have a buddy with them.
*[Kirby] Are there other examples
of risk reduction? *
[Dr. Kaye Whitley] I'm not familiar,
but that's out of my area of expertise.
$$ August 1, 2011,
Major General Mary Kay Hertog
replaces Kaye Whitley as the Director
of the Sexual Assault and Prevention Office. $$
[Major Gen. Mary Kay Hertog] Well,
I want to continue where Dr. Whitley left off.
Looking at where our focus is and that's
on prevention as well as response,
we've really done a very good job there
and the credit goes to Dr. Whitley
and her staff that has been working this
the past five to years years.
[Rep. Mike Turner] I don't think
the Department of Defense
has really yet embraced that they have
a sexual assault problem
that its not just an issue
of a cultural environment
or that the people at risk
of sexual assault.
The system itself does not value
the rights of victims
and doesn't provide them
adequate protection.
[Major Gen. Mary Kay Hertog] You know,
I have heard the accusations as well,
that commanders are sweeping this
under the carpet.
Now, what I would say to the people
that have come forward to you is that,
if you feel that your commander is
ignoring what you have asked them to do,
if they are not taking care of you
within that chain of command,
you need to go to the DOD,
the Department of Defense Inspector General.
[Rep. Jackie Speier] The GAO,
General Accounting Office,
just did a study, a report and guess what,
not one, not one case,
of more than 2,500 has been reviewed
and investigated
by the inspector general,
and when asked about that,
the inspector general said,
"Well, we have other higher priorities."
[Susan Burke] What you really want
is you want there to be a system akin
to a civilian system
where you go to the police
and the crime is prosecuted
by an impartial judicial system.
[Major Gen. Mary Kay Hertog]
As a commander, you have no favorites.
You are equally to take care
of every single person
in your organization.
That's what command is all about.
[Rep. Susan Burke] These are
human beings just like everyone else.
You cannot be impartial when you
are involved with people in other settings.
[Admiral Anthony Kurta] I would take
exception with your characterization
that the disposition of the case
is based on the relationship
between the commander
and the alleged perpetrator.
$$ 33% of female soldiers
didn't report their rape
because the person to report to
was a friend of the rapist. $$
[Major Gen. Mary Kay Hertog]
I'm going to speak to you
with my former commander's hat on.
There is absolutely
no conflict of interest.
You do what the right thing is to do.
You have other avenues and if you feel like you
have not been taken care adequately
by your commander,
go up through your congressman,
or congresswoman,
file a complaint that way.
[Rep. Susan Burke] You can't go to your congressman
to obtain justice for being raped,
I mean, imagine how silly that is,
imagine if you told civilians that,
"Oh jeez, sorry you were raped,
go talk to your congressman."
$$ Many of our closest NATO allies
no longer allow commanders
to determine the prosecution
of sexual assault cases. $$
*[Amy] If you could say something
to this guy,*
what would you want to say to him?
[Jessica Hinves] I don't know.
I don't think it's affected his life at all.
And people in my old squadron
that I've talked to,
they don't see an effect on him at all,
and that hurts
because it's a struggle every day
and it's completely changed who I am.
[Kori Cioca] I'm really hoping he falls off
a coast guard boat
and they never find him.
I'm really hoping for that.
Or there's a poor mishap
and got chopped up by the prop.
[Rob McDonald] That would be great.
[Kori Cioca] That would be great.
[Rob McDonald] That would be
an exciting day.
[Kori Cioca] It would.
I'd probably celebrate.
[Trina McDonald] I hope this
reaches them too, you know.
I hope that somewhere
someone sees my face,
you know, wherever it is, and goes,
"I know them.",
and they're talking about me
because they know what they did.
And then all they'll have to mutter
is to some friend that goes,
"Hey weren't we stationed with her?"
and then it can't be a secret anymore.
So hopefully they have to deal with it too,
you know,
in some way shape or form.
[Helen Benedict] Most rapists
are repetitive criminals.
It's a kind of crime
that has an obsessive quality
so people do it again and again.
So the tragedy of that is
that every one of these guys
who gets off freely, will be doing it
to other women, again and again,
often for years and years and years.
[Russell Strand] The average sex offender
in their lifetime has about 300 victims,
and the vast majority of sex offenders
will never be caught.
[Myla Haider] A lot of civilians see it
as being a military problem,
but it really isn't. Because 5% or less
of reported offenders are convicted,
so almost none of them wind up
on the sex offender registry.
[Major Gen. Mary Kay Hertog]
There is no military sex offender list
that I'm aware of but, if you're convicted
in court, a felony conviction
of sex offense of a sex offense,
you're going to go on the national list.
*[Kirby] For any sex offense whatsoever? *
[Major Gen. Mary Kay Hertog] Correct.
[Stace Nelson] That is not the case.
It depends on what level conviction they got.
If they received over a year,
then that's considered a felony.
But a lot of these cases are plead down,
so that they're not felonies.
The military doesn't like
to prosecute people
and keep them as felony convictions.
[Russell Strand] I often ask myself
the question, "Why would they stop?",
and if there's nothing to stop them
like incarceration,
or some other major life change,
they're going to continue.
[Stace Nelson] If you run
a sexual predator
through the judicial system
and then you slap him on
the hand all you've done,
is you've done the equivalent of the
catch and release program.
You've caught them,
you've educated them,
and now you've released them back
into hometown America.
He now knows a lot more
about the law enforcement,
the judicial system, than he did
when he first started,
which makes him a much more
capable criminal,
and a much more dangerous criminal.
[Capt. Anu Bhagwati] They go on to
literally prey on women and men
in our neighborhoods
across the United States.
If we don't care about women and men
in the military, then we should hopefully care
about women and men, girls and boys
in our neighborhood back home.
$$ In December 2011, the Court dismissed
the survivor's lawsuit ruling that rape is an
occupational hazard of military service.
An appeal has been filed. $$
[Helen Benedict] The thing that broke
my heart the most about this story,
was the young women who went in
with such idealism,
I want to serve my country,
I want to give back.
To see a young person's hope and idealism
crushed in that brutal way,
I think we owe our young people
more than that.
[Rep. Chellie Pingree] Increasingly,
women are becoming
some of the best‐trained officials
that we have in the military.
These are great soldiers
and we can't afford to lose them.
[Sara Albertson] Yeah, I'm happy
I never have to wear that again.
[Paula Coughlin] People deeply believe
in their hearts to serve their country.
They should be given that chance,
with respect.
You know, it's part of really
our American way.
[Kori Cioca] Do you think we deserve
a purple heart
because we were wounded
in a time of war?
[Regina Vasquez] They're never going
to give us one.
[Kori Cioca] I know, but I'm just saying
maybe there should be a ribbon
for women who have survived it.
[Dennis Laich] We have a good army,
a good military, but not a great one
and this is the kind of issue that keeps
our military from being great.
[Brigadier Gen. Loree Sutton] We can
view this as a shared challenge.
It's not just a woman's issue,
it's not just something
the military has to deal with,
but it's society.
We're all in this together.
It's our national duty.
$$ Five, years after her attack,
Kori is still trying to get coverage
for her jaw surgery from the
Veterans Administration.
Her assailant is still in the Coast Guard
and lives in Charleston, South Carolina. $$
$$ Ariana is pursuing her Masters Degree
in Social Work to help survivors
or military sexual assault.
Her assault was court‐martialed
and found guilty of adultery and
indecent language. $$
$$ Elle is working for a corporation
and lives in South Carolina.
Her assailant has recently been promoted
to lieutenant colonel. $$
$$ Michael and his wife are helping
promote awareness
of male military sexual assault.
He does not know the identity of his assailants
or where they are today. $$
$$ Jessica and her husband had a baby boy
and are raising him in Virginia.
Her assailant is still in the Air Force
and was awarded 'Airman of the Year'
during her rape investigation. $$
$$ Hannah's father, Jerry,
is returning from Iraq
after a one‐year deployment.
Her assailant is still in the Navy
and stationed three hours
from her home in Kentucky. $$
$$ Myla's assailant became a supervisor
at a major U.S. corporation
and sexually assaulted a
female employee.
He was never charged
and now lives in Queens, New York. $$
$$ Sign the petition to take the decision
to prosecute and investigate rape
out of the hands of commanders.
Go to invisiblewarmovie.com. $$
$$ Seek ways to help MST survivors.
Volunteer at your local VA Center.
Host a screening of this film.
If everyone knows, it can't be a secret. $$
$$Listen to a veteran and ask them
to share their story.
Let them know they are not invisible. $$